Guide to Videorecordings of Civil Rights Movement Speakers at SUNY Geneseo
State University of New York at Geneseo
Videorecordings of Civil Rights Movement Speakers at SUNY Geneseo
2003 - 2017
SUNY Geneseo's Commemoration of the life and work of Martin Luther King, Jr. is an annual event and includes keynote addresses by distinguished speakers. Many of these speakers also visit classrooms to engage students in more intimate discussions involving race, rights, and justice in America.
20 digital videorecordings
State University of New York College, Geneseo
SNCC Digital Gateway
None
SUNY Geneseo, as an integral part of its annual Commemoration of Martin Luther King, Jr., brings distinguished scholars and figures of the civil rights movement to campus to speak on issues of race and social justice. Geneseo's Commemoration is guided by the following understanding of King's life and legacy.
Martin Luther King, Jr., is the most visible leader of the modern Civil Rights Movement. He came to prominence during the 1955 Montgomery Bus Boycott after he was drafted as a reluctant leader. In the process, he began to develop the ideas of nonviolent resistance -- as tactic and philosophy -- that are closely associated with him. An effective and charismatic speaker, King was skilled at reaching multiple audiences and drawing on and synthesizing ideas from multiple traditions. Decades after his death, many of us are still moved by his words and vision. Unfortunately, however, our culture has done much to sanitize King. We have frozen him in 1963 giving his famous "I Have a Dream" speech. We forget that when King was assassinated, he was under attack for speaking publicly against the United States' role in the Vietnam war and that he was organizing an interracial Poor People's Campaign intended to bring assertive nonviolent resistance to the nation's capitol. When our political and civic leaders draw on King's words and legacy, they tend to emphasize his advocacy of nonviolence and his dream for a "color-blind" society. They ignore his later calls for affirmative action and the redistribution of wealth. They obscure his criticism of the United States as a purveyor of violence around the world.
In honoring Martin Luther King, it is important that we remember the full range of his social justice work and the ways that he evolved over the course of his life. We must also understand that King did not create the Civil Rights Movement. Rather, an extensive mass movement propelled him forward. It is really meaningless, then, to memorialize King separate from the larger struggle and the work and commitment of countless women and men. In joining people across the country in honoring King, the Geneseo community is particularly concerned with recognizing and acknowledging King's enduring commitment to social justice and to the ways that King's leadership reflects a broader tradition of struggle.
The Civil Rights Movement has been called the "Borning Struggle," the inspiration and model for the many progressive movements that emerged out of that movement. Geneseo's King Commemoration honors and acknowledges the individual contributions of Martin Luther King and the expansive movement for social justice that he was a part of and which continues today.
King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968; African Americans--Civil rights--History; Civil rights movements--United States; Bond, Julian, 1940-2015; Cobb, Charles E., Jr.; Dennis, David J.; Bender, Rita L.; Bender, William J.; Blackwell, Unita, 1933-; Donaldson, Ivanhoe; Robinson, Betty Garman; Greene, Freddie, 1945-; Ladner, Dorie; Lawson, Jennifer, 1946-; Clark, Colia L. Liddell Lafayette; McDew, Charles; McLaurin, Charles; Redden, Shaketa; Richardson, Judy, 1944-; Simmons, Gwendolyn Zoharah; Varelo, Maria, 1940-; Watkins, Hollis, 1941-; Zellner, Bob; Zellner, Dorothy; Snead, Chanel
SUNY Geneseo's Commemoration of the life and work of Martin Luther King, Jr. is an annual event and includes keynote addresses by distinguished speakers. Many of these speakers also visit classrooms to engage students in more intimate discussions involving race, rights, and justice in America.
Recordings are arranged alphabetically by speaker's last name, then chronologically by type of event (keynote, classroom discussion, interview, etc.)
- Bender, Rita Schwerner, 2013
  - Classroom visit (with Bill Bender), April 2, 2013
    Watch now!
  - Classroom visit (with Bill Bender), April 2, 2013
- Bender, William "Bill", 2013
  - Classroom visit (with Rita Bender), April 2, 2013
  - Classroom visit (with Rita Bender), April 2, 2013
- Blackwell, Unita, 2004
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Charles McDew and Bob Zellner), April 15, 2004
- Bond, Julian, 2007
  Julian Bond was a charismatic figure of the 1960s civil rights movement, a lightning rod of the anti-Vietnam War campaign and a lifelong champion of equal rights, notably as chairman of the N.A.A.C.P.
  - King Commemoration keynote, October 24, 2007
  - Interview, October 24, 2007
- Cobb, Charles, 2009 & 2014
  Charles “Charlie” Cobb joined the civil rights movement in Mississippi at the age of nineteen. While on his way to an activism workshop in Texas, Cobb stopped in Jackson, Mississippi to meet the students sitting-in there. Local students challenged Cobb to stay in Mississippi and join their efforts. There, he helped to start the second voter registration campaign in the Mississippi Delta. Cobb placed a great emphasis on local leadership, insisting that “Mississippi’s Movement was led by Mississippians, not by the Charlie Cobb’s coming down from Howard University or wherever… That’s what organizing for voter registration was about – challenging people in various ways to take control of their own lives.” Similarly, Cobb believed in the organizing abilities of young people. In 1964, he wrote a memo proposing Freedom Schools to “Fill an intellectual and creative vacuum in the lives of young Negro Mississippians.” For more information, see SNCC Digital Gateway @ https://snccdigital.org/.
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Dorie Ladner, and Charles McLaurin), April 21, 2014
  - Classroom visit (with Dorie Ladner and Charles McLaurin), April 22, 2014
  - King Commemoration keynote, March 1, 2009
  - Classroom visit, March 1, 2009
  - Classroom visit (with Dorie Ladner and Charles McLaurin), April 22, 2014
  - Classroom visit (with Dorie Ladner and Charles McLaurin), April 22, 2014
- Dennis, Dave, 2008
  Dave Dennis participated in the first Freedom Bus ride from Montgomery, Alabama to Jackson, Mississippi in 1961 as they were attempting to desegregate the interstate bus system, and in voter registration efforts during the 1964 Freedom Summer.
  - King Commemoration keynote, January 31, 2008
  - Classroom visit, January 31, 2008
- Donaldson, Ivanhoe, 2013
  - Classroom visit #1, April 18, 2013
  - Classroom visit #2, April 18, 2013
  - Classroom visit #3, April 18, 2013
- Garman, Betty, 2012
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Judy Richardson and Dorothy Zellner), March 8, 2012
- Greene Biddle, Freddie, 2017
  Freddie Greene Biddle was born in 1945 to a family of activists. The Greene family had been some of SNCC’s earliest supporters in Greenwood, Mississippi. This made them the target of some violence, as the Greene house was shot at in 1962. Despite this, Greene and her older brothers began to participate in mass meetings and voter registration drives. Green later left college to work for SNCC full-time. Greene participated in SNCC’s McComb project in 1964, working to register voters and helping out in the freedom schools. Later, she was recruited to work in SNCC’s national office in Atlanta, where she worked the switchboard.
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Jennifer Lawson and Shaketa Redden), April 3, 2017
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Jennifer Lawson), April 4, 2017
  - Fireside chat (with Jennifer Lawson), April 3, 2017
- Ladner, Dorie, 2014 & 2016
  Dorie Ladner and her sister Joyce were raised in Hattiesburg, Mississippi, to family that stressed activism and racial pride. The Ladner sisters had a close relationship with many important civil rights leaders such as Clyde Kennard, Medgar Evers, and Vernon Dahmer, president of the Forrest County branch of the NAACP. Dahmer helped the Ladner sisters form an NAACP Youth Council in Hattiesburg, and brought them to statewide meetings in Jackson. In 1961, Dorie Ladner joined the “Tougaloo Nine,” a group of students who were arrested and for trying to integrate a library in downtown Jackson. As a result, Dorie was expelled from Jackson State. Although she enrolled at Tougaloo College, Dorie dropped out of college three separate times to focus on SNCC, declaring, “I can’t stay in school and know my people are suffering.” During her time working for SNCC, she worked on voter registration in the Delta and later became Project Director in Natchez, Mississippi.
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Charles Cobb and Charles McLaurin), April 21, 2014
  - Panel discussion (with Colia Liddell and Chanel Snead), October 25, 2016
  - Classroom visit (with Charles Cobb and Charles McLaurin), April 22, 2014
  - Classroom visit #1 (with Colia Liddell), October 25, 2016
  - Classroom visit #2 (with Colia Liddell), October 25, 2016
  - Classroom visit (with Charles Cobb and Charles McLaurin), April 22, 2014
  - Classroom visit (with Charles Cobb and Charles McLaurin), April 22, 2014
- Lawson, Jennifer, 2017
  Jennifer Lawson, born in 1946, first joined the Civil Rights Movement as a high schooler in Birmingham, reflecting “you could not help but be a part of the Movement.” In 1963, she joined the week-long protests and was temporarily expelled as a result. Later, she left college to become a full-time SNCC field secretary. As an organizer in Lowndes County, Alabama, Lawson worked on voter registration and promoted the Lowndes County Freedom Organization, the independent political party SNCC was building with local residents. As an amateur artist, Lawson dedicated her talents to the effort, drawing the illustrations for a comic book to help educate local people on the functions of the county offices. Later, she became the head of programming at PBS and started her own media company.
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Freddie Greene Biddle and Shaketa Redden), April 3, 2017
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Freddie Greene Biddle), April 4, 2017
  - Fireside chat (with Freddie Greene Biddle), April 3, 2017
- Liddell, Colia, 2016
  - Panel discussion (with Dorie Ladner and Chanel Snead), October 25, 2016
  - Classroom visit #1 (with Dorie Ladner), October 25, 2016
  - Classroom visit #2 (with Dorie Ladner), October 25, 2016
- McDew, Charles "Chuck," 2003 & 2004
  - King Commemoration keynote, March 13, 2003
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Unita Blackwell and Bob Zellner), April 15, 2004
- McLaurin, Charles, 2014
  A native Mississippian, Charles McLaurin joined SNCC’s first voter registration efforts in the Mississippi Delta at the age of twenty-one. There, McLaurin and other SNCC workers placed a great emphasis on working with the community and involving local leadership. They visited churches, homes, barbershops, and helped local residents with their daily work. McLaurin described the importance of community, saying, “Talk with the people, laugh with them, joke with them; do most anything that gets some attention on you, or on some kind of conversation. It is very important to learn what bugs them.” McLaurin worked closely with Fannie Lou Hamer, a native Mississippian and local community leader. When Mrs. Hamer ran for Congress with the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party in 1964, he served as her campaign manager. Later, he helped Mrs. Hamer start the Freedom Forms Cooperative.
  - King Commemoration keynote, April 21, 2014
  - Classroom visit (with Charles Cobb and Dorie Ladner), April 22, 2014
  - Classroom visit (with Charles Cobb and Dorie Ladner), April 22, 2014
  - Classroom visit (with Charles Cobb and Dorie Ladner), April 22, 2014
- Redden, Shaketa, 2017
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Jennifer Lawson and Freddie Greene Biddle), April 3, 2017
- Richardson, Judy, 2005 & 2012
  - King Commemoration keynote, March 4, 2005
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Dorothy Zeller and Betty Garman), March 8, 2012
- Simmons, Zoharah, 2017
  - King Commemoration keynote, February 20, 2016
- Snead, Chanel, 2016
  - Discussion panel (with Dorie Ladner and Colia Liddell), October 25, 2016
- Varela, Maria, 2007
  - Interview, April 1, 2007
  - King Commemoration keynote, April 2, 2007
- Watkins, Hollis, 2010
  Born in 1941, Hollis Watkins was one of the first young Mississippians to commit to full-time work with SNCC. At age 19, he was recruited by Bob Moses to join the voter registration effort in McComb, Mississippi. Watkins’ youth made him a role model for many high school students in McComb, encouraging them to join the Movement. Watkins was elected president of the Pike County Nonviolent Direct Action Committee. He and Curtis Hayes, the Committee’s vice-president, began the sit-in movement in McComb when they sat down at a Woolworth department store lunch counter and were consequently arrested. Their arrest only spurred further direct action in McComb. Later, Watkins traveled to Hattiesburg to work as a SNCC field secretary, assisting NAACP leader Vernon Dahmer in voter registration. Watkins also worked in Greenwood in 1962, then began activism efforts in Holmes County as well.
  - King Commemoration keynote, March 4, 2010
  - Classroom visit, March 4, 2010
  - Classroom visit, March 4, 2010
- Zellner, Bob, 2004
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Charles McDew and Unita Blackwell), April 15, 2004
- Zellner, Dorothy, 2012
  - King Commemoration keynote (with Judy Richardson and Betty Garman), March 8, 2012